בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*.
Okay, today's דף *daf* is י"ז *Yud Zayin*, and we are at
the very top of י"ז *Yud Zayin*,
the first line אלא *Ela*. And the discussion here has been the
following: We had a line in the משנה Mishnah *Mishna* that says
you can always שחט shecht *shecht*. Or now, as I said, this
is unquestionably the simple sense of this is referring back to the
line that you can שחט shecht *shecht* at night. But the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is choosing to interpret this differently, and first wanted to
interpret it in light of רבי ישמעאל'ס Rabbi Yishmael's *Rebbi Yishmael's* statement
that בני ישראל Yisrael *Bnei Yisrael* were when they were in the
מדבר midbar *midbar*, in the wilderness, they could not eat meat unless
they brought it as a קרבן korban *korban*.
And when they got into ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael. *Eretz Yisrael* and
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. *Beis Hamikdash* was far away, they were
told that they could eat meat even without bringing it as a
קרבן korban. *korban*. So this משנה mishna *Mishna* is teaching that even
though now they're not in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael. *Eretz Yisrael* anymore,
the allowance still applies and you're still allowed to eat meat, you
can שחט shachat, *shecht* all the time. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* rejected
this or challenged this because it said number one, it should have
emphasized eating, not שחטינג *shechting*. And number two, obviously you can שחט
*shecht* meat nowadays because the whole problem was the need to bring
it as a קרבן korban. *korban*. So if you can't bring it
as a קרבן korban, *korban*, like in Israel when you're far away
and certainly nowadays when there's no בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beis Hamikdash*,
it should be obvious that meat is allowed. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* rejected that as the interpretation and now let's take a look
at the next possible possibility, which is a variation of that. So
top of י"ז עמוד א' *Yud Zayin Amud Aleph*, אלא אמר רב
יוסף *Ela Amar Rav Yosef*, so רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* said רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva היא *Rebbi Akiva hi*, it's רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
*Rebbi Akiva* that disagrees with רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael *Rebbi Yishmael*. What
does רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rebbi Akiva* say? דתניא *DeTanya*, we taught
in a ברייתא *Baraita*, כי ירחיב ה' אלהיך את גבולך כאשר דבר
לך ואמרת אכלה בשר כי תאוה נפשך לאכל בשר ki te’aveh nafsh’cha
le’echol basar, בכל אות נפשך תאכל בשר כי ירחק ממך המקום אשר
יבחר ה' אלהיך לשום שמו שם וזבחת מבקרך ומצאנך v'zavachta mi-bekarcha u-mi-tzoncha.
*Ki yarchiv Hashem Elokecha et gevulcha ka'asher diber lach ve'amarta ochla vasar
ki te'aveh nafshacha leechol basar bechol avat nafshacha tochal basar. Ki yirchak
mimcha hamakom asher yivchar Hashem Elokecha lasum shemo sham vezavachta mivekarcha umitzonecha*.
So this is the same verse רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael, *Rebbi Yishmael*
was talking about: when you come into the land of Israel and
the place of God's dwelling, the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. *Beis Hamikdash*
is distant, then you shall slaughter from your cattle and from your
sheep wherever you are. So רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael *Rebbi Yishmael* taught
from that that you don't have to bring them as a קרבן
korban *korban* if you want to eat meat and the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash *Beis Hamikdash* is far away, you can go ahead and
eat meat wherever you want, the concept of בשר תאוה basar ta'ava?
*Basar Ta'avah*, the meat of desire. So how does רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva *Rebbi Akiva* read it? רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva אומר *Rebbi Akiva
omer*, a very shocking read, לא בא הכתוב אלא לאסור להם בשר
נחירה Nechira *Lo ba hakatuv ela le'asor lahem basar nechira*. The verse
is coming to forbid for them once they go into the land
of Israel, meat of puncturing. The word נחירה nechira *nechira* is really
sort of like the opposite of the word שחיטה shechitah *shechita*. It
means a way of killing an animal not through proper שחיטה shechitah.
*shechita*. It could mean that you sort of stab into the neck
rather than slice, or it could mean that you slice from the
word נחירה *nechira* refers to like your nostrils, so it might mean
you slice from the sort of top of the animal's mouth, like
close to the nostrils and do in a downward rather than in
an across motion, it's a vertical motion. But whatever the word נחירה
*nechira* means, it means basically killing an animal without slaughter. So רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, *Rebbi Akiva* makes a shocking thing, he says the
Torah talks about slaughtering their animals once you bring them into the...
once you come into the land and the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
*Beis Hamikdash* is distant, which means that when they were in the
מדבר midbar, *midbar*, in the wilderness, they were allowed to eat meat
without the act of שחיטה shechitah *shechita*, without slaughter, which is of
course totally wacky because you know, what would be the logic for
this? You know, there they are, the משכן Mishkan *Mishkan* is close,
they can bring a קרבן korban, *korban* whenever they want, but if
for some reason you don't want to bring a קרבן Korban, *korban*
and you just סתם *stam* want to eat meat, then there's no
ritual thing to be done with it.
If you do want to bring a קרבן Korban, *korban* you have
to שחט *shecht*.
Right, and that we're going to say, if you do want to
bring a קרבן Korban, *korban* you still have to שחט *shecht*. So
you know, to... I mean the only logic I can give for
this and it's not a good one and it really seems wild
is that... that the primary ritual associated with meat was obviously
the bringing of a קרבן Korban *korban*. That he agrees with רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael *Rebbi Yishmael*. So that's going to be not only
the ritual of bringing it as a sacrifice, but how the animal
is slaughtered, all those rituals are around the קרבנות korbanot. *korbanot*. So
if the משכן Mishkan *Mishkan* is so close and you're always having
the opportunity to do that, even though you don't always must do
it, you're allowed to eat meat, but you're always having the opportunity
to do it, there's no need if you would to have any
special rituals associated with meat outside of that because you so frequently
have those rituals in the context of קרבנות korbanot *korbanot*. Once you
come into ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael, *Eretz Yisrael* where you don't have
קרבנות korbanot *korbanot* so frequently, so you're... it's very distant from you,
then you're going to need more rituals regularly associated with meat, you're
going to need the שחיטה shechitah *shechita*. It's... I'm... it's not a
fully satisfying explanation, it's a very strange position, but that is what
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, *Rebbi Akiva* says. So let's... Does it also
relate to...
to the view that they did not... they were not required to...
to keep כשרות kashrus *kashrut* in general?
Oh, when they went and conquered the land. So we're going to
get to that, but that's only for the seven years of conquering,
that doesn't apply for the period that they were in the מדבר
midbar, *midbar*, in the wilderness.
Right, but there's something
about this as being not yet real time.
Not yet real time. Real time only begins after they've come into
the land. Something like that. Maybe, maybe something like that.
Maybe they say because they were busy, you're not telling everybody.
Right, right, right.
Could be. So let's take a look.
Okay, so רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, אומר לא בא כתוב אלא לאסור
להם בשר נחירה שבתחילה הותרה להם בשר נחירה.
The meat of puncturing, of non-שחיטה shechitah. was allowed to them. ומשנכנסו
לארץ, U-mishenichnesu l'aretz,
once they came into the Land of Israel, נאסר להם בשר נחירה.
ne’esor lahem basar nechirah. Then it says oh, now you’re in the
land, if you want to eat meat, you should וזבחת, ve-zavachta, slaughter,
it has to be through
שחיטה. shechitah ועכשיו, Ve-achshav, I might have thought, ועכשיו שגלו, ve-achshav she-galu,
now that they went into exile, יכול יחזרו להיתירן הראשון, yachol yachzeru
le-heteiran ha-rishon, maybe it's going back to like the time pre-the-Temple. So
when Israel is somehow not in its, you know, ideal state in
the Land of Israel with the Temple, maybe this type of meat
is permissible without slaughtering. לכך שנינו, L'kach shaninu, therefore we say לעולם
שוחטין, le-olam shochtin, you have to שחט at all times, even nowadays.
So again, this is very bizarre. What is the logic to say
that just because there's no Temple, all of a sudden these allowances
should apply? And it's sort of what the גמרא Gemara challenged earlier.
It says, you know, if you're saying that you weren't allowed to
eat meat when there was a, you know, in the wilderness, it
doesn't mean now you're not allowed to, there it's because of the
closeness of the Temple. So here too, what's the logic? Apparently the
גמרא Gemara is not bothered with the logic as long as it's
not like obviously wrong. The argument that maybe nowadays you can't eat
meat in the גמרא'ס Gemara's eyes was obviously wrong. The whole problem
with eating meat in the wilderness was the opportunity for bringing קרבנות.
korbanot So it could not contemplate the possibility that you can't eat
meat nowadays if קרבן korban, is not a possibility. Here however, whatever
the logic is and we don't understand the logic, it's a wild
idea that you didn't need שחיטה shechitah? but for whatever reason you
didn't need שחיטה shechitah, when there was no בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash,
So maybe now there's also no בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash maybe you
also don't need שחיטה. shechitah So therefore we say you do. Okay,
but obviously these ideas are wild to imagine that this would be
the case and obviously we're saying in practice they're not. But that's
what the משנה mishna, is coming to teach you, that nowadays you
still need שחיטה shechitah even though there's no בית המקדש. Now we're
going to take some time to reflect on this debate of Rabbi
Akiva and Rabbi Ishmael. Yes.
Could that be kind of metaphorically the hope and prayer and the
belief that there will be a בית המקדש in the future?
Well sure, but how does that have to do with the fact
that if there's no בית המקדש you don't need שחיטה?
shechitah, No, no, I'm thinking of
the idea you don't need, of you can't eat meat. Right, that
idea actually of the two ideas was the one that was a
little bit more logical. You could somehow say that the whole idea
of eating meat, you know, is a special allowance and maybe it's
only allowed when sort of, you know, when the, when things are
ideal, when we're in גלות galus and are less than ideal, you
don't have this allowance of eating meat, you know, you could have
said something about that. This is even wilder. Why? Because there's no
Temple should we be allowed to, you know, not not have to
slaughter meat? Not, so the possibilities are, it's very hard to understand.
The גמרא'ס Gemara's now going to just focus on this debate itself,
so let's take a look.
במאי מפלגי? B’mai miphligi? What are they debating? רבי עקיבא סבר בשר
תאוה, Rabbi Akiva savar basar ta’avah, meat of desire, meaning the eating
meat not in the context of קרבנות korbanot because of basing itself
on the biblical verse that says כי תאוה נפשך לאכל בשר, your
soul desires to eat meat. So this meat of desire לא אסר
כלל, lo assar klal, was never forbidden. So if the תורה Torah
is making a distinction between when before they came into the land
and after, it's about the need to do שחיטה, Shechita, but the
תורה Torah is not actually forbidding meat outside of a קרבן. korban.
רבי ישמעאל סבר, Rabbi Ishmael savar, no, the opposite, בשר נחירה לא
אישתרי כלל, basar nechirah lo ishtari klal, that the תורה Torah never
would have permitted meat that wasn't slaughtered. So if the תורה Torah
is making a distinction between before and after entering the land and
building the בית המקדש, the distinction is not whether you need to
slaughter, the distinction is whether you're allowed to eat meat. So this
really does not explain their debate, this just rephrases their debate. Okay,
yes, one of them is saying that the issue was about allowing
meat with not requiring שחיטה Shechita and the other says the issue
was allowing meat to be eaten not as a קרבן. korban, So
now we're going to look at the verses. בשלמא לרבי ישמעאל, Bishlama
le-Rabbi Ishmael, it works according to Rabbi Ishmael, היינו דכתיב, hainu de-chtiv,
that's what the verse means when it says ושחט את בן הבקר.
ve-shachat et ben ha-bakar. This is the very beginning of the פרשת
ויקרא Parshas Vayikra where it speaks about bringing קרבנות Korbanot, and it
says you shall slaughter. So you see here you're bringing קרבנות Korbanot,
and you're slaughtering. According to Rabbi Akiva it sounds like he said
there's no such thing as שחיטה Shechita. before they entered into the
Land of Israel. So what do you do with that verse? אלא
רבי עקיבא מאי ושחט? Ela Rabbi Akiva mai ve-shachat? What does it
mean slaughtering, which obviously means ritual slaughtering? So he says קדשים שאני,
kodshim shani, sacrifices are different. Sacrifices of course always required ritual slaughtering.
What Rabbi Akiva was saying was that meat not in the context
of קרבנות Korbanot. before they entered the land they did not need
to slaughter it. Which is really wild. Right? On the one hand
you have the משכן Mishkan right there, you have a constant opportunity
to bring קרבן, korban when you're bringing קרבן korban. it has to
be through an act of שחיטה, Shechita, but if you're choosing not
to bring a קרבן, korban. just go ahead and shoot
the animal in the head, not a problem.
What about ושחט את בן הבקר, ve-shachat et ben ha-bakar, that wasn't
a?
We're going to get to that. Okay Charlie, yes? That verse is
from ויקרא פרק א Vayikra Perek Aleph which talks about עולות. olos.
Right. You don't eat an עולה. olah. bring קרבנות, Korbanot when you
bring a קרבן, korban it has to be through an act of
שחיטה, Shechita. but if you're choosing not to bring a קרבן, korban.
just go ahead and shoot the animal in the head, not a
problem. What about שחיטת חולין? Shechitat Chullin? What? שחיטת חולין, Shechitat Chullin,
that wasn't a... We're going to get to that. Okay, Charlie, yes?
That verse is from ויקרא Vayikra פרק א, Perek Aleph, which talks
about עולות. Olot. Right. You don't need an עולה. Olah.
Oh, that's an interesting point. But I guess the גמרא's Gemara question
is, is that, is that you see that the concept of שחיטה
Shechita was already present. So how could you say there was no
concept? And the answer was yes, it was present by קרבנות, Korbanot
it was not required by non-קרבנות. korbanot Okay, so now where are
about 20 lines from the top where near where it says במדבר
יח Bamidbar Yud-Chet in the right hand column there, yes?
But wouldn't you be wasting if you didn't do it correctly the
קרבן, korban. you'd be wasting the animal so there'd be בל תשחית.
Bal Tashchit.
No, but we have to argue first that it was required. So
that's the point, that was it actually required? Yes. You're assuming if
it was required obviously you had to do it. Yeah, but we're
questioning whether or not it was required.
Well what would you do if it wouldn't be?
Yeah, then it would not be valid. Right. Okay so the גמרא
Gemara says like this.
Okay. בשלמא לרבי ישמעאל היינו דכתיב, Bishlama L'Rabbi Yishmael hainu d'chtiv, it
works for רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael because that's what the verse says,
הצאן והבקר ישחט להם, Ha-tzon v'ha-bakar yishachet lahem, that when משה Moshe
talks to God about how can you give them all the meat
that they want, he talks about slaughtering flock and cattle. So you
see that in order to eat it it required slaughtering. אלא לרבי
עקיבא, Ela L'Rabbi Akiva, but according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who
said that when they were in the wilderness they could eat meat
without slaughtering it, מאי הצאן והבקר ישחט להם? Mai ha-tzon v'ha-bakar yishachet
lahem? What does that mean, that would you slaughter all the sheep
and cattle? You don't need שחיטה. Shechita. ינחר להם מיבעי ליה, Yinacher
lahem mibaye lei,
so it should have said if you should just, again this word
נחירה which means kill, kill without the act of ritual slaughter. So
why does it say ישחט? Yishachet? Let it say if you will
just kill
sheep and cattle. So the גמרא Gemara says you're right, that's what
it means. נחירה שלהם זו היא שחיטתן. Nechirata shelahem zu hi shechitatan.
Since in that period according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva? they did
not need a ritual שחיטה, Shechita. so any form of killing would
be called שחיטה. Shechita שחיטה Shechita? did not have the connotation, which
is actually a good point because if you ask yourself if you
just simply read the verses in the תורה Torah you never get
a sense that there's a specifically defined ritual of שחיטה. Shechita I
mean maybe we do, but probably because we're bringing our pre-existing lens
that we know there's a ritual of שחיטה. Shechita But the word
שחיטה Shechita just means slaughter, right? So who's to say that it
means a ritual שחיטה? Shechita. What about זביחה? Zevicha? Also slaughter. So
the גמרא Gemara assumes that words like שחיטה Shechita? and זביחה Zevicha
mean ritual slaughter but there's nothing intrinsic in that word. So that's
what it's saying here. You're right. According to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
he would read the word שחיטה Shechita prior to for this period
of the wilderness to just mean slaughter without ritual slaughter. Okay, it
only becomes a ritual demand or requirement once they enter into the
land and presumably the reason I would say and this is maybe
Michael's question, so how does he know it ever becomes a ritual
demand? So maybe it is the shift from the word שחיטה Shechita
to זביחה Zevicha because it says you'll come into the land
וזבחת מבקרך, v'zavachta mi-bekarcha,
maybe he thinks the word וזבחת v'zavachta has greater weight. But I
think it's more than that. I think for once the תורה Torah
is actually commanding the act. Until that point anytime it talks about
killing animals it's always descriptive, right? I mean ושחט, v'shachat, ישחט להם,
yishachet lahem, ושחט, v'shachat,
maybe you could say by the קרבנות korbanot, it's also commanding the
act although there he admitted that by the קרבנות it was שחיטה.
Shechita Okay, but in terms of eating non-קרבן korban meat the only
time the תורה Torah rather than just describing slaughtering commands it, right?
The תורה Torah never says you must slaughter the meat following certain
הלכות, halachot, right? There's never a thing like that. The whole idea
that you need requirements on a particular act is very not obvious
in the תורה. Torah. The one פסוק pasuk that commands the slaughter
of non-קדשים, kodashim, non-sacrifices, is this פסוק pasuk in דברים Devarim that
we started with. You'll come into the land, the בית המקדש will
be distant, וזבחת מבקרך ומצאנך. So since there it's a command in
the context and could be read as a command in the context
of non-קדשים, kodashim, non-sacrifices, that I believe is why he is saying
that
it refers to the ritual, but prior to that there was not
a particular ritual. James, you had a question?
How does רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva reconcile all the comparisons we make
to the עקידה Akeidah when it says when we use that
word?
That you require a knife and so on, right. Well maybe maybe
that was קדשים. kodashim.
It's a good question.
I mean there also לשחוט את בנו, lishchot et bno, right, right.
Kill him anyway which way?
Yeah I understand, I understand.
But they drew a proof?
Yeah it's a nice question. It's a nice question. I mean yeah
again unless you would say some קדשים kodashim argument but then how
do you apply it to חולין? chullin? Right. It's a nice question.
Okay, yeah, at the end of the day how do we know
then you need like an act of שחיטה?
shechita Basically הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai. I mean all the
requirements, yeah, yeah. I mean but חז"ל Chazal generally insist that the
word שחיטה shechita and זביחה Zevicha mean ritual slaughter but here רבי
עקיבא says not necessarily.
Okay, so let's take a look.
Okay. בשלמא לרבי ישמעאל, Bishlama L'Rabbi Yishmael, so it works well according
to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, היינו דתנן. hainu d'tenan. השוחט ונתנבלה בידו,
Hashochet v'nitnavla b'yado, if somebody does שחיטה shechita. and it becomes a
נבלה nevela by hand meaning he does the שחיטה shechita, incorrectly, he
puts pressure, he tears, והנוחר, v'ha-nocher, you do this נחירה which is
let's say poking or cutting lengthwise rather than widthwise, והמעקר, v'ha-me'aker, or
you he uproot... Uproots one of the סימנים, simanim, the trachea or
the esophagus without cutting it or before cutting it, פטור מ, patur
mi, so basically he's made the animal, he didn't שחט the animal
properly, so this is a case of the question here under discussion
in this משנה Mishnah. is covering the blood. Right, the תורה Torah
says that if you slaughter a חיה chaya or an עוף, of,
again, not a בהמה, behema, not cattle or sheep, but something like
deer or birds, chicken, you have to cover the blood. So it's
only, says this משנה, Mishnah if it was slaughtered correctly. If it
wasn't slaughtered correctly, you made an error in the שחיטה shechitah. or
you did it lengthwise or whatever you did wrong, then you don't
have to cover the blood. But you only have to cover the
blood if it's slaughtered correctly. Okay, in all these cases פטור מלכסות,
patur mil'chasot, you don't have to cover the blood. So we understand
that according to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael, why? Because when the תורה
Torah commanded covering the blood, and that was commanded before they entered
into the land of Israel—all the commands in the תורה Torah were
given before they entered into the land of Israel—so according to רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael at that time there was still a conceptual distinction,
right, between—there was a distinction between slaughtering correctly and slaughtering incorrectly. You
still had to slaughter correctly. So when the תורה Torah commanded covering
the blood, it could have been only in the case when it
was slaughtered correctly. But according to רבי עקיבא, at that time when
they were still in the wilderness, they didn't—it didn't matter how they
slaughtered it, and the תורה Torah still said cover the blood. So
why don't we then take that logic and apply it even after
you have to do the ritual slaughtering and say nevertheless the מצוה
mitzvah of covering the blood when originally given
applied regardless of how the slaughtering was done? Okay, so that is
the question. I'll get to your hand in a minute Charlie, let's
just see the answer.
And so the גמרא Gemara. says אלא לרבי עקיבא מאי פטור מלכסות.
ella leRabbi Akiva mai patur mil'chasot. According to רבי עקיבא, why are
you exempt from covering the blood? Since when the מצוה mitzvah of
covering the blood originally applied, it did not matter—there was no concept
of ritual slaughtering. So his answer is הואיל ואיצטר איצטר. hoil ve'itztar
itztar. No, once the תורה Torah made it forbidden to eat the
meat without ritual slaughtering, once those new laws applied when they went
into the land of Israel, then obviously everything had to now be
revised, you know, retroactively. So now the slaughtering—when there was no ritual
slaughtering and it was always כשר, kosher, you had to cover the
blood in all circumstances. Now that the meat is only כשר kosher
when you do the slaughtering in a particular way and there is
a concept of ritual slaughtering, then you only cover the blood when
that ritual is done properly. Yes, Charlie.
This is strange according to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael because we would
not have been שוחט-ing shochet a חיה chaya when we were in
the מדבר plain of Moab?
Oh, that is a good question. You mean because of בשר תאוה?
basar
ta'ava But actually no.
I think תוספות Tosafot asks that question and basically says, or somebody
asks that question, basically says that no, because since those could not—a
חיה chaya and עוף of could not have been brought as a
קרבן, he would have admitted that that you would have been allowed
to bring even in the—even in the מדבר, even when—Oh wow. Yes,
because the whole problem that you could not eat the other meat
was that you should—you know, the reason בשר תאוה basar ta'ava was
not allowed was that it was supposed to be brought as a
קרבן. So things that you did not have the potential to bring
as a קרבן, you would have been allowed to eat.
But you could have brought a deer as a שלמים? shelamim?
No, not as a שלמים. shelamim. You could have a deer to
eat as meat. As meat? Yes. The only thing you could not
eat as בשר תאוה—as basar taava, meat outside of קרבנות—was meat that
you could have brought as a קרבן and therefore you should have
brought as a קרבן. Right. Okay. But yes, that's a very good
question. So I believe תוספות Tosafot says that. Okay, so anyway so
now the גמרא Gemara goes on... where are
we? Okay, היינו דאיצטר איצטר. hainu de'itztar itztar. בשלמא לרבי עקיבא, bishlama
leRabbi Akiva, it works well according to רבי עקיבא, דאמר בשר תאוה
לא איצטר כלל, de'amar basar ta'ava lo itztar klal, that says they
were never forbidden to eat meat of desire, you know, so that
they could have always had any meat they wanted.
דהיינו דכתיב, dehainu d'chtiv, that's what the verse means when it says
אך כאשר יאכל את הצבי ואת האיל כן תאכלנו. ach ka'asher ye'achel
et hatzvi v'et ha'ayal ken tochlenu. Right, when it speaks about that
if you have a sacrifice that became invalid and that you redeem
it, so then it says you can slaughter this in your gates,
meaning although it once was a sacrifice, now it's been redeemed, you
don't have to bring it as a קרבן. The same way you
would eat the צבי tzvi and the איל, ayal, the deer and
the... what's the איל? ayal? What? Hart? Hart. Is that what an
איל ayal is? He says? Okay. I thought it was something else.
I thought it was—okay, whatever, a gazelle or an ibex. I don't
know. Whatever. The deer and the hart, so shall you eat it.
Okay, which means that you don't have to, you know, you don't
have to worry about it becoming טמא. tamei. It's not a קרבן
anymore. Fine. But you understand why it's comparing it to the... to
the צבי tzvi and the איל ayal or whatever, the deer and
the hart, because it's basically saying the same way these are permissible,
that's permissible. But according to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael actually here the
גמרא Gemara. exactly does address this question about what's the story with
חיה. chaya. According
to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, צבי ואיל גופיה מי הוה שרי? tzvi
ve'ayal gufeih mi havah shari? So,
I'm sorry, so I was attributing it to תוספות, Tosafot, it's really
the next line in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. So the—the deer and
the hart, you know, why—they weren't—we don't know yet that those are
permitted, that the תורה Torah should be using them as an example
of permitted meat. Because everything is forbidden until—until they go into the
land. So the גמרא Gemara says no, כי אסר רחמנא בבהמה. ki
asar Rachmana be'behema. כי אסר רחמנא בהמה דחזיא להקרבה. ki asar rachmana
beheima dechazya lehakerava. There it is, right in the גמרא. Gemara When
did the תורה Torah according to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael say you
cannot eat meat outside of the משכן when they were in the
wilderness? That was only cattle that could have been brought as a
sacrifice. אבל חיה, aval chaya, but you know, the wild animal, חיה
chaya like a deer, דלא חזיא להקרבה delo chazya lehakerava that never
would have been fit for a sacrifice, לא אסר רחמנא, lo asar
rachmana, the תורה Torah never would have forbidden. So when the תורה
Torah speaks, so yes, so according to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael again
where are we? The תורה Torah says specifically when you come into
the land you'll have a temple, but it'll be far away, so
it's okay you can eat meat in your gates. So רבי ישמעאל
unquestionably gives the simplest read of this verse, which means you no
longer have to bring meat as sacrifices, you can eat them without
bringing them as sacrifices because the temple was too far away. Okay,
which is meaning and that's the standard way in which everybody reads
those פסוקים pesukim like רבי ישמעאל, that there was a
presumed prohibition of eating בשר תאוה, basar taava meat of desire outside
of not as a non-sacrifice when they were in the wilderness because
the משכן was so close. Here we're seeing, well maybe that's only
things that could have been brought as קרבנות, maybe things like deer
would have been different, but nevertheless basically don't eat it if you
could bring it as a קרבן. When they go ahead and enter
into the land and the and the temple is very far away,
then they're allowed to eat them, even then בשר תאוה basar taava,
becomes permitted, they're allowed to eat it without a קרבן. It also
fits in, works in very nicely you know to contemporary attitudes towards
consumption of meat and vegetarianism and so meaning even those that are
not vegetarians, but the idea of not to take consumption of meat
for granted and that fundamentally, you know, it started in the context
of a of of only within a like a religious act and
bringing as a קרבן and then it was only like an allowance
to human's weakness, בשר תאוה, that it was allowed in other circumstances,
but it not fundamentally, it's meaning it fundamentally is somewhat problematic, not
fundamentally not problematic. And חז"ל Chazal sometimes reflect this issue as well,
you know, you should only eat meat you know only sort of
like on rare occasions, not on a regular basis, I mean we'll
see some of those statements later. Anyway, so that's for רבי ישמעאל'ס
approach which is exactly the more simpler sense of the verse. רבי
עקיבא gives a very bizarre read, which is hard to understand at
all what the sort of theology behind it is, you know, philosophy
behind it is, which is that they didn't have to do ritual
ritual slaughtering for sacrifices when they were in the wilderness, any other
meat they could eat however they wanted, and it was only when
they came into the land of ישראל Yisrael that then they had
to start doing ritual slaughtering. Very strange to understand you know why,
why that would be. It's also like other questions could be asked,
why does the תורה Torah forbid נבילה neveila according to רבי עקיבא?
Why is a נבילה neveila different than other you know it's an
animal that died, so what? So how's that different if there's no
concept of שחיטה shechitah. yet?
David, yes, you had one word comment to help you understand? Please.
רוסו. Rousseau. רוסו. Rousseau. Oh, well that explains it. Yeah. You want
to elaborate a little, unpack that?
אידך פירושא זיל גמור.
idach perusha
zil gmor.
The French philosopher?
Yeah, I know who he is, I'm not that...
state of nature is the ideal state, man living in that environment.
The תורה Torah comes to bring us to something different.
So but but I understand, but I'm just not sure why all
the other מצוות mitzvot applied in the wilderness except for this particular
one. But okay, anyway, we can we we can work that out.
Yes, but but what I find interesting is though
if רבי ישמעאל is really not so keen on you eating meat.
Well he never said that exactly, but okay anyway yeah right. Okay
yeah.
But isn't there even ואכלת את שלל אויביך? veachalta et shelal oyvecha?
We'll get to we'll get to that a little bit right now.
So let's see the next line of גמרא. Gemara.
What does it imply? What? In the מדבר, at least one other
in the קרבן פסח. korban Pesach.
Right, right, that was held in... yeah.
You can say all that.
I mean there are a couple obviously the מצוות mitzvot that relate
to the agriculture of ישראל Yisrael, don't apply, I mean you know,
so.
ברית מילה. Brit milah. ברית מילה Brit milah applied. I mean when
they they didn't do it because they were... there was סכנה sakana
to do it since they were traveling but it technically applied. Okay
so now we're going to turn to some to a question that's
broached earlier. בעי רבי ירמיה, Ba'ei Rabbi Yirmeya, רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmeya
asks, second wide line.
אברי בשר נחירה שהכניסו ישראל עמהן לארץ. evrei basar nechira she-hichnisu Yisrael
imahen la-aretz. So according to רבי עקיבא that they didn't have to
do שחיטה. shechitah Presumably like I said there was still a concept
of נבילה neveila if the animal dies, but they could kill it
in any way as long as it was killed through human agency.
Okay so let's say they did that, they they killed it in
some other way you know through slitting the throat up and down
rather than across, poking it, whatever they did, and then they had
some nice a nice thigh here or some ribs and right before
they went into the land of ישראל, Yisrael right before משה Moshe
died, they had done this and they had some you know they
had rack of lamb and now and now they're entering into the
land of ישראל Yisrael? and they haven't yet eaten their rack of
lamb and they want to eat it now that they're in the
land. So now that they're in the land they have to do
שחיטה, shechitah. but this was killed before they entered it. Does it
now become טריף treif or does it does it get grandfathered in
since it was it was killed before they entered into the land
of ישראל? Right, exactly. Okay what's that call? Kobe, Kobe? What? Kobe
beef? Kobe. Yeah, but that's not particularly aged. They have stuff like
aged like. Yeah, what? Okay, anyway. All right, anyway, so what's the
story? אבר בשר נחירה שהכניסו ישראל עמהם לארץ מהו? Avar basar nechira
she-hichnisu Yisrael imman la-aretz mahu? What's the law? אימת, eimas, when are
you asking about this question? אילימא בשבע שכבשו, iy-leima b'sheva she-kivshu, the
seven years of conquering the land? השתא דבר טמא אישתרי להו. hashta
davar tamei ishtarei lehu. They were allowed to eat even non-kosher food
during that period, דכתיב ובתים מלאים כל טוב, dichshiv u'vatim malei'im kol
tuv,
that you will see there when you conquer the land houses filled
with all good things. ואמר רבי ירמיה בר אבא אמר רב: v'amar
Rabbi Yirmiyah bar Abba amar Rav: כתלי דחזירי, kitzlei d'chazirei,
that they could even eat the
dried pork, dried pig that they found in the land. They conquer
a house, they see whatever food is in the house, they're allowed
to eat it even if it's non-kosher. So if they could eat
that, בשר נחירה מיבעיא? basar nechira miba'aya? Is there any question that
they could eat this meat that was not properly slaughtered? אלא לאחר
מכאן. ella l'achar mikan.
They were really aged, so somehow all these, this rack of lamb
they managed to preserve it and now they want to eat it
eight years later after they've conquered the land, where they're not allowed
to eat non-kosher food. And now they want to know, can they
eat because it was slaughtered incorrectly but that maybe should be grandfathered
in because that was before they entered into the land. That's the
question. ואיבעית אימא, v'ibayis eima, if you want, לעולם בשבע שכבשו. l'olam
b'sheva she-kivshu. We would actually,
we would be talking during the seven years of conquering, so it's
only
like a month after they originally killed it. וכי אישתרי להו, v'ki
ishtarei lehu, what was permitted to them when they were conquering the
land? שלל של עובדי כוכבים. shalal shel ovdei kochavim. It was only
the booty of the non-Jews whose land they were conquering, whose houses
they were taking over. דידהו, did-hu, their own food, לא אישתרו, lo
ishtarv, was not permitted. So therefore it's not that there was a
general waiving of laws of כשרות kashrus during those seven years, it
was much more specific. In the process of conquering, as if you
take over stuff, you kept booty from their things, you are allowed
to eat it. Now one way to understand this is obviously you're
fighting a war, you might not always have time to worry about
כשרות kashrut, and there's סכנה sakana issues and so on and you
have to eat what you have available. But the גמרא Gemara actually
is saying more than that because it's actually saying if that was
true it would not have been a special statement here about this,
it would generally be true about סכנה sakana issues. I mean, so
what it seems to be saying is that since God is giving
you the booty of the land and the booty of your enemies
and whatever you conquer, part of what you're entitled to is to
benefit from it even if it's not kosher. A special waiving of
laws of כשרות, kashrut a very, also very strange idea, but that's
only to benefit from the booty. That's not a waiving of laws
of כשרות kashrut. for all those, for that whole period of time.
So therefore we want to know what is the story about this
stuff, does it get grandfathered in or not? And the גמרא Gemara
says תיקו, teiku, it doesn't have an answer to that. And with
that we end our little look at the רבי עקיבא and רבי
ישמעאל debate. Charlie.
This would also seem to be a waiving of the laws of
עבודה זרה avodah zarah because some of this food would have been
dedicated to.
That's an interesting question.
Would it have been in their houses? I don't know, because the
Torah says presumably the stuff that would have been dedicated would have
been in the temples, the offerings. And there the Torah is very
clear about destroying שקץ תשקצנו shakeitz t'shaktzenu and everything, לא ידבק בידך,
lo yidbak b'yadcha, destroying everything that has to do with עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah. And you know, I mean it is interesting if you
go back to the story about יעקב, Yaakov, remember what יעקב Yaakov
says to his family: הסירו את אלהי הנכר אשר בתוככם
והטהרו,
hasiru et elohei hanachar asher
b'tochechem v'hitaharu, right? So obviously when you take booty you're taking over
all the little gold idols and whatever types of things. Right, but
that is an interesting point but I, that is never stated and
I think that that would have, you know, I don't know if
anybody discusses that but intuitively I would say that would be completely
rejected because the whole other emphasis in the Torah is you will
encounter all of this nice gold and silver related to the עבודה
זרה avodah zarah and you absolutely need to keep distant and destroy
it. So that would be the exception to this general permission.
In my mind there's no question that that's not being included here,
it speaks specifically about כשרות. By the way, did anybody hear they
just found in one of these I think Buddhist temples, what was
it like, twelve billion dollars worth of things that were dedicated to
it in a treasury? So amazing. Anyway. Yeah, yeah. Yeah, I mean
people over years had brought offerings, not animal sacrifices, gold and silver
offerings, they put it in some treasury, it had been locked or
whatever, they opened it up and they sort of you know saw
what they had, it was like I think twelve billion pounds worth
of gold and silver and various precious things.
Yes, so pounds
meaning British pounds, not weight.
If they recover gold idols and melt it down, is it still
forbidden?
Yes, that's what we discussed in עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, unless it
goes through a process of annulment through that the non-Jews who worshipped
it annul it, but otherwise it remains forbidden. Yes.
Just comparing to
today, if you go fight a war in Israel, can you eat
the.
No no no, this was specifically during that period. conquering of the
land of Israel. Otherwise, other questions of סכנה sakanah would apply. Oh,
you mean when they would? Yeah, חז״ל Chazal only apply it to
those first seven years. That's an interesting point. But חז״ל Chazal only
apply it to those first seven years. Okay, so now let's continue
in the גמרא. Gemara So that's one read of the whole idea
of לעולם שוחטים, Le'olam Shochtim, which is definitely a stretch in our
משנה. Mishnah? So now we get to more reasonable read. אמר רבא,
Amar Rava, שניתא הכל שוחטין. Shanita Hakol Shochtin. So Rava says look,
the משנה Mishnah. says you shecht everything, and which we said you
shecht with everything really, oh excuse me, everybody shechts is the simple
read of that, but you have chosen to read it to mean
you shecht all things, that even birds require שחיטה. shechitah, ולעולם שוחטים,
Ule'olam Shochtim, you shecht it all times, which now we're saying means
that you know, that now you never go back to allowing things
without שחיטה. shechitah So בכל שוחטין, Bechol Shochtin, how about the third
phrase of the משנה? Mishnah, You can shecht with all things. מאי
משני ליה? Mai mashni leh? How do you, how are you going
to interpret what that phrase means? וכי תימא, Vechi teima, let's say
you interpret it in a natural way, בין בצור בין בזכוכית בין
בקרומית של קנה, bein betzur bein bizchuchit bein bikrumit shel kaneh, like
the משניות mishnaiyot have been saying, you know, whether with a rock
or with a glass or with a reed. So דומיא דהנך קתני,
dumya dehanach kataney, it should be similar to the other two. So
אי הנך בשוחטים האי נמי בשוחטים. ee hanach beshochtim hai nami beshochtim.
So if the earlier ones are referring to the act of שחיטה
shechitah, itself, then I can say like you would say that the
בכל שוחטין, Bechol Shochtin, what objects can you mean, means doing the
act of שחיטה. shechitah. Okay, what does that mean? In contrast to
what? Here's what it's in contrast to. אי הנך בנשחטים, ee hanach
benishchatim, but that's not how you explained the first phrases. Remember, how
did the גמרא Gemara explain הכל שוחטין? Hakol Shochtin? It explained it
doesn't mean all people can shecht, it wasn't talking about the act
of שחיטה, Shechita, it said all animals need to be shechted. So
if you're going to explain some of the earlier phrases not in
terms of the act of שחיטה but what requires שחיטה, if that's
true, האי נמי בנשחטים, hai nami benishchatim, so you would have to
explain the last phrase of using all objects referring to the, not
the act but the things upon which it's done which obviously does
not work. So Rava is basically saying in a, you know, that
this is a convoluted way of explaining this משנה. Mishnah, If it
says all can shecht, it doesn't mean you shecht all things. It
means you can always shecht. It means at all times, it does
not mean that you know, we still require שחיטה. And certainly the
last phrase you can use all objects clearly goes back to earlier
ideas that we stated about which types of objects can be used.
אלא אמר רבא, Ela amar Rava, so rather Rava says here's how
to read the משנה, Mishnah. which is how we would have read
it from the beginning. הכל שוחטין, Hakol Shochtin, all can shecht. חדא
לאתויי כותי וחדא לאתויי ישראל מומר. chada le'atuyei kuti vechada le'atuyei yisrael
mumar. So what does it mean all people can shecht? We've already
said who, it's like the first משנה, Mishnah. all people can shecht.
What does that include? Even a כותי, kuti, even a ישראל מומר
yisrael mumar that's a habitual sinner. That was some of our very
early discussions of that משנה. Mishnah, So it's basically echoing the first
משנה. Mishnah לעולם שוחטים, Le'olam Shochtim, you can shecht it all times,
בין ביום בין בלילה בין בראש הגג בין בראש הספינה. bein beyom
bein balailah bein berosh hagag bein berosh hasfinah. Also going back echoing
an earlier משנה, Mishnah whether day and at night, whether on the
top of a roof or whether on a boat, actually that's not
so much about all times but at least all places. Right. Okay.
Remind you about Sam I Am. Would you shecht it on a
boat? Would you shecht it
on a, okay. בכל שוחטין, Bechol Shochtin, okay, בין בצור בין בזכוכית
בין בקרומית של קנה, bein betzur bein bizchuchit bein bikrumit shel kaneh,
and with all things, whether with a rock, reed or a glass.
So basically what he's saying is echoing exactly the structure of the
earlier משניות, mishnaiyot, which is of course what we would always assumed.
The reason it's, what he is also answering subtly here is the
reason it's being repeated, why is it being repeated? That's what pushed
the גמרא Gemara to give this weird read to this. Why already
said it, why repeat it? Is it's saying it's expanding the category
a little more. So our first משנה Mishnah said everybody. Maybe that
only meant a כותי. kuti. It says it again here everybody, even
a ישראל מומר. yisrael mumar. The first משנה Mishnah. says whether day
at night, but what about doing it on a rooftop? So the
second time it says לעולם le'olam is to include even like on
a rooftop or on a boat. The first משנה said you can
use a rock. But what about a reed? What about a piece
of glass? So it says it a second time to include that.
But it is basically echoing the earlier statements and expanding them a
little bit. Okay. So that is that phrase in the משנה. Now
we go back to the exact objects that are being used. חוץ
ממגל קציר והמגירה. Chutz mimagal katzir vehamigerah. You cannot use a harvesting
scythe which has obviously serrated and you know, teeth and you can't
use a saw. Okay, so which is basically you have to use
something that has a sharp smooth cutting, you know, edge, not something
with serrations. And now we are going to get into a very
technical or whatever, not so technical but a very, you know, specific
discussion about the sharpness of the knife and the problem with nicks
and, okay, so let's take a look. אבוה דשמואל, Avuha diShmuel, the
father of Shmuel, there is
often the father of Shmuel in contact with ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisroel.
So what he doing? פגם ושדר פגם ושדר. Pagam veshadar pagam veshadar.
He would make a nick in a knife and send it to
ארץ ישראל. Make a nick in a knife and send it to
ארץ ישראל, meaning he wanted to get information about what types of
nicks are problem
or. שלחו ליה. Shalchu lei. So they
apparently sent back to him כמאגרה שנינו. kimagaira shaninu. The problem is
only if it's like a saw. Okay, which is going to mean
and I'll tell you in a minute here. Can you hand me
that big book right there that says שיחת חולין? Sichas Chullin? The
one... no... there... yeah. This... this has great pictures. I mean this
is also a picture book and has more photographs, but this has
very clear diagrams which are great. Basically, the difference is going to
be whether the point of a serration is like... you know it's
like a V comes up like that and has an edge on
both sides. Okay, and the problem there is that whichever way you
hit it, it's going to tear rather than cut. Right? Or if
it's basically pointed only on one side and a... well, here I'll
show you the picture. So it only tears in one direction.
Which means it doesn't have to
be in the
middle of the knife, what you're saying. It could be in the
middle of the knife, but the question is what the nick looks
like. Okay. So here for example, I don't know if you can
see that... this... if you see... let me see if I have
one that's a little bit clearer. Okay. So for example, look at
this. Okay. You see this... this one down here where it sort
of it has all these levels, right? But... because... but they're only
sort of a problem in one direction. If you're going this way,
it's sort of bumping down but it's not actually hitting a rise.
If you don't hit a rise, right? It's... you see it goes
sort of like this. Right? So... so then it doesn't... if it
doesn't hit a rise, it's not tearing. It only tears when it
hits a rise. So as opposed to the bumpy V-shaped, if the
bump... if it was more like this, right? So if you're going
this way... if you're going this way, it... the sort of the
thing, you know, slides down here and continues cutting. It's only if
it's going this way and it hits here and it has to
come up and then continue that it causes
the rise and
if it's a V, it's... it's always a problem. But if it's
like this, it's only a problem in one direction. What...
is this only a problem with דריסה derisa though?
Oh, you mean... I don't... that's an interesting... I mean, I think
that if you're not pressuring... you mean because then you're... you have...
you have to move the knife slightly. But when you're moving it,
if you're... you're moving it through air... if you're sort of you
know you're cutting here and then it's sort of it... you know
the skin is following the movement
of the knife...
would
cause a certain amount of... yeah, apparently not. It's a good point,
but apparently not. Okay, so that's the issue. That is going to
be the key difference here in terms of what the... what the
bump looks like. So let's take a look. Okay, כמאגרה שנינו. kimagaira
shaninu. It's only a problem if it's like a saw, meaning with
a serration... also a bump on both sides.
Yeah, do you have an extra long knife so you only go
one way?
Yeah, we're... we're going to talk about that. Yes. תנו רבנן, Tanu
Rabbanan, let's take a look. סכין, Sakin, a knife, שיש בה פגימות
הרבה, sheyesh bah pgimos harbe, if it has a lot of... a
lot of nicks, a lot of serrations, כדון כמאגרה, kidon kimagaira, it's
like a saw, meaning even if those serrations are of this type
that they are, you know, only one direction. By the way, you
see this a little bit like you know in the rental cars,
right? Do not back up, right? Because if you go over one
way, it's totally smooth, right? You go over the other way, it
wears your... it tears your tires to shreds.
I wonder if they
use those in ארץ ישראל. Really? So there you can see that
you can have something that is extremely sharp and tearing but only
if you approach it one way. Okay. Nevertheless, the assumption here is
that although it's not tearing if you go the right way, because
of the bumping, it is going to weaken the skin and it
will sort of have a... so the גמרא's Gemara assumption is that
you cannot allow that to happen more than once. So even this
type of a bump, which is not particularly tearing, that only works
if it's a single bump. But if it's multiple bumps, then the
skin will get torn eventually as a result of that as well.
So you could have a knife like that before... as a... it
is possible? It is... it is possible. It's only כשר kosher if
there's only one. Okay, so if it has multiple bumps, even if
they are of the better types of bumps, כדון כמאגרה, kidon kimagaira,
then it's like a saw. ושאין בה אלא פגימה אחת, v'she'ein bah
ela pgima achas, if it has only one of these nicks, then
it matters what type of a bump it is. אוגרת פסולה, ogeres
psula, a gathering bump. רש"י Rashi says because it means like the
skin gathers into the crevice, you know, if you've got V-shapes, there
are crevices. So that anyway means a double-edged bump. That's invalid. מסוכסכת
כשרה, mesuchsaches k'sheira, if it is more of a rubbing that type
of a bump, meaning it's only one direction, then it's okay if
it's a single bump. So a single bump is okay if it
is the one that is more... that is only one directional and
assuming you're going in the right direction to avoid... prevent the problem.
Okay, so let's take a look. אמר רבי אליעזר, Amar Rabbi Eliezer,
אוגרת משתי רוחות, ogeres mishtei ruchos, and here you have it very
clear. אוגרת ogeres means that it's on two sides, and מסוכסכת מרוח
אחת, mesuchsaches meruach achas, the rubbing one is only a problem on
one direction. מאי שנא משתי רוחות? Mai shina mishtei ruchos? So now
the גמרא Gemara says why is two directions a problem? דמורשא קמא
מחליש ומורשא בתרא בזע. d'mursha kamma machlish umursha basra baza. The first
sort of you know inclination causes the skin to be weakened and
then when it comes back it tears it. the second one tears
it. So it first hits if you've got this V, right? It
hits it here, and that sort of, you know, weakens the skin,
and then as it's coming down, the skin is or the סימן
siman is torn. So the גמרא Gemara says if that's true,
מרוח אחת נמי? mi-ruach achas nami? Why don't we say even if
it's only one bump? חורפא דסכינא מחליש. Churpa d'sakkina machlish. After the
skin has gone over the knife, right, obviously it's already been weakened,
which also means by the way that you're torn through the outer
layer, you've torn through the skin and the flesh and now because
the only time we really care about the tearing is when you
get to the סימנים, simanim, the trachea or the esophagus. So if
you've got a knife, I've cut through, assuming the bump is at
the end, I've cut through, I've exposed the trachea and the esophagus,
now this bump is going to come in contact with the trachea
and the esophagus, so even if it's of the more gentle bumps,
it should be enough to do this tearing now that it's hitting
the exposed trachea and the esophagus. That's the גמרא's Gemara question. It
assumes that it does have the potential to do some degree of,
you know, roughness because the same reason we said before that two
of those bumps are also a problem. So it's not that those
bumps are non-problematic, they're just less of a problem. So the גמרא
Gemara says so okay, the sharpness of the knife exposes the trachea
and the esophagus, מחליש. machlish.
מורשא בזע, Morsha baza, when it hits the actual inclination itself, that's
what it should cause a tearing. So the גמרא Gemara, says אה,
דקאים ארישא דסכינא. Ah, d'kayim a-reisha d'sakkina. Okay, so the bump is
at the very beginning of the knife. So when the bump originally
contacts the animal's neck, it's only touching the skin and the flesh.
It's not yet touching the trachea and the esophagus. Okay, so you've
got this one gentle bump at the beginning of the knife, so
it's only going to whatever type of problem is caused by it
is only when it's in contact with the skin
and not when the knife gets to the trachea and the esophagus.
So the גמרא gemara says if that's true, how about like Michael
said, but you move the knife in two directions? So the גמרא
says סוף סוף, sof sof, nevertheless at the end of the day,
כי אזלה מחלשה, ki azla machlisha, when you do in one direction
it weakens, כי אתא ki asa when it comes in the other
direction בזע baza it tears. So you're going to move the knife
back in the other direction and by that time the trachea and
the esophagus will be exposed, and this bump should tear it. So
it says כגון שהוליך ולא הביא. kigone she-holich v'lo heivi. Like Michael
said, it's a very long knife and you're only moving it in
one direction. So in the end the גמרא, although it makes this
big difference between the type of the bumps, we have the only
case where there's any bump that's okay, you know, נקיצה niktza that's
okay, is like almost non-existent. It's that it's the right type of
נקיצה, niktza, it's only one direction, not two directions. It's at the
very beginning of the knife, so it'll only come in contact with
the throat and with like the flesh, not with the trachea and
the esophagus, and the knife is long enough so you're never going
to bring the knife back in the other direction. So basically the
upshot is all nicks are a problem. Okay?
We won't worry that maybe at some point you'll bring
it back in the other... well, that is also true that there's
a לכתחילה l'chatchila problem as well. So let's take a look. Okay.
אמר רבא: Amar Rava: ג' מידות בסכין. gimmel middos b'sakkin. There are
three types of characteristics of a knife. Yes,
I'm sure it's not dumb. Go ahead.
שחיטה, so they do it in how many times do you pass
it back and forth?
What? Well, you so, the knife is supposed to be long enough
for the entire width of the neck of the animal. So then
you and you have to do it twice. If you make the
knife long enough doubled width of the neck of the animal, you
only have to do it once. But you basically
have to do as much cutting that equals twice the width of
the animal's neck. So if the knife is the width of the
animal's neck, you have to do it twice, and if it's double
the width you do it once.
Okay.
What? Is that a minimum or a standard?
That is a minimum. Yeah, you can certainly cut more after you're
done, it's a minimum. Yeah. Okay. The real question is how do
you do it if in theory the knife could even be shorter
than the animal's throat if you can sort of the angle would
be a problem, you know what I mean? Because how do you
get it to be flat? But in theory as long as you
do the sufficient amount of cutting the actual blade could even be
shorter than the animal's neck. Okay. Yes. All right. So let's take
a look.
Where are we? ג' מידות בסכין. gimmel middos b'sakkin. אוגרת, Ogeret, if
it's this type of a gathering, meaning a bump on both edges,
לא ישחוט ואם שחט שחיטה פסולה. lo yishchot v'im shachat shchitah p'sula.
בדיעבד B'di-eved it's invalid. We assume that it tears and does not
it's not the sharpness.
מסוכסכת Mesuchsachet is more a rubbing bump which is only permitted in
very narrow circumstances. לא ישחוט בה. lo yishchot bah. Here to address
Michael's concern. Don't do it לכתחילה l'chatchila because you're obviously asking for
trouble. ואם שחט, V'im shachat, but if you did it and assuming
that you satisfied all the requirements we just talked about about one
direction and only at the top etc., then שחיטה כשרה shchitah k'sheira
בדיעבד b'di-eved it's okay. עולה ויורד, Oleh v'yored, if it is something
that is not really it's more like a grad it's a bump.
I've been actually saying bump, but I really should have been saying
more like a notch or a
serration, right? you could imagine that the knife is sort of like
a little bumpy like this, but it's not really going down at
any sharp angle, right? It's sort of soft curves. So that is
called עולה ויורד, ole veyored, which means okay, it's not totally straight,
but there's nothing that's going to cause any type of catch or
nicking or any type of tearing, okay? It's just sort of, you
know, a very gradual sort of change in the in the things.
I'll see if I have an example here.
It's like, it's like hilly as opposed to.
Hilly, right, exactly. Low hills.
Kitchen knife actually has a point at the end.
Kitchen knife, here's an עולה ויורד ole veyored example here. You see
that? So like obviously the it'll it'll travel along, but there's nowhere
for anything to get caught and for anything to tear. Okay? So
that type of a case,
עולה ויורד בסכין שוחט לכתחילה. ole veyored besakin shochet lechat'chila. That you
can even use לכתחילה. lechat'chila. אמר ליה רב הונא בריה דרב נחמיה
לרב אשי. amar leh rav huna berei de'rav nechemya le'rav ashi. So
he says, so Rav Huna said to Rav Ashi, אמרית לן משמיה
דרבא, amrit lan mishmei de'rava, you said to us in the name
of Rava, מסוכסכת פסולה, mesuchsachet pesula, that if it's this rubbing type
of a nick, the better notch, it's invalid. והא אמר רבא והתניא
ve'ha amar rava ve'hatanya whatever it is, מסוכסכת כשרה, mesuchsachet keshera, but
we talked that this better type of a nick, this rubbing nick
is kosher? לא קשיא, lo kashya, כאן שהוליך והביא כאן שהוליך ולא
הביא. kan she'holich ve'heivi kan she'holich velo heivi. Exactly this issue, that
did you go over it once or twice? If you only went
over it once and in the in the non-tearing way, then it's
okay. But if you went back and forth with it, so on
the way back it hits the, you know, it hits the tearing
side, then it is going to be invalid.
You went like this and then like this again?
I guess you could, but that would that would probably that might
be שהייה, shehiya, although not, no, שהייה shehiya does take a a
few seconds. So if you're quick enough, you probably could do that
without doing שהייה, shehiya, but that's not the natural motion. The natural
motion is that you're going to go back and forth.
But once you cut the trachea and esophagus even if you go
back isn't it already sort of done even if you go back?
You know, that's a good point, we assume that the reason for
the double length or for the you know going twice the width
is to get into this to get is is to get to
the trachea and esophagus. What would happen if you're saying if you
if you did it first time you did it, I guess the
question is could you really do that without דריסה? derisa? Could you
really do that without pressure? Remember you're not allowed to, I think
the assumption is is that because you're not applying any pressure, you
need one width to basically expose the trachea and esophagus and the
other width to actually cut them.
It's a field trip.
Yes! You know, we definitely should maybe try to arrange that. I
don't know, would people really go if I could arrange it? Yes!
Show of hands. If I could arrange this visit to a slaughterhouse.
No! Let Andy come and give us. All right, oh that's not
a bad idea. Okay, I have to fly him in or something.
Okay, a video on the blog.
That is true, there are videos to be seen, but it's not
the same as seeing it in person, you know? Okay, so the
גמרא says like this. Okay. Okay. Let's take a look. אמר ליה
רב אחא בריה דרב אויא לרב אשי, amar leh rav acha berei
de'rav avya le'rav ashi, so the so this question was asked to
Rav Ashi, דמי לסאסאה מאי, dami lesasa'a mai, if it's like a
סאסאה, sasa'a, which is basically like the the the strands that come
from a barley thing and I have no idea why that is
being used to describe the idea of this knife, but basically it
means a knife that as I said is sort of somewhat not
a straight edge, but there's no actual notches. It's sort of like,
you know, wavy, right, a wavy type of a knife. עולה ויורד?
ole veyored? Yeah, something like that.
Is that different than עולה ויורד?
ole veyored? No, it's not really different than עולה ויורד. ole veyored.
It seems like it's maybe multiple עולה ויורד, ole veyoreds, okay? It's
not exactly clear how different it is. אמר ליה, amar leh, he
said back to him, מאן יהיב לן מבשרא ואכלינן, man yahiv lan
mibishra ve'achlinan, he said I'll be the first to eat from the
meat of that animal, okay? If somebody would just give us that
meat I'd eat from it, meaning it's absolutely no problem, invite me
to the barbecue. Okay.
So I'm reading here from the commentary here that the the barley
thing is like they're very, very fine bumps. Oh.
Oh, that they're very fine.
They're very fine and not enough to cause any tearing? Yes.
Really? That is very interesting. רש״י rashi did not sound like that.
רש״י rashi says שאינו חלק כסכין שפיה חלק אבל פגם אין לה.
she'eino chalak kesakin she'piah chalak aval pegam ein lah.
So he says so maybe that's how you know whoever who's that
reading that way? Steinsaltz? Maybe that's what he's reading רש״י rashi that
it's not a פגם pegam meaning it's not a deep enough serration.
Um, this book at least the picture that it had for that
was,
yeah I mean here's the picture it had which is even less
than עולה ויורד. ole veyored. I mean basically you have to look
at it close up. He basically says if you rub your finger
on the edge it'll feel rough but there's no notches at all.
That sounds like what רש״י rashi is describing, you know? He just
shows like he says if you rub your finger you feel like
it feels a little bumpy, it feels a little rough, like almost
like an unsharpened knife but there's no notches. That seems to be
what רש״י rashi is describing and I guess עולה ויורד ole veyored
is more is a bigger
bump, right. You rub your finger, it feels rough like sandpaper.
Exactly. Really? Yeah, well, that we're going to get right now into
checking knives. So let's take a look. Okay. אמר רב חסדא *Amar
Rav Chisda*, מניין לבדיקת סכין *Minayin L'Vdikat Sakin*? So now we move
from what are the problems to the idea of checking the knives.
מניין לבדיקת סכין מן התורה *Minayin L'Vdikat Sakin Min HaTorah*, where do
you see that there's an idea in the Torah to check your
knife? שנאמר *Shene'emar*, well, whatever, we'll see, anyway presumably before, וזבחתם בזה
ואכלתם *Uz'vachtem Bazei V'achaltem*. By שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel*, now this is not
in the Torah, but anyway he says you shall slaughter with this
and you shall eat. So presumably he checked the knife and said,
yeah, good knife, here take this knife and do the שחיטה *shechitah*.
That's how they're reading the verse. Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara* says,
פשיטא כיון דאי
פגמה טרפה treifah,
בעי בדיקה *Pshita Keivan D'Ee Pagma Treifa Ba'ei Bdika*. Of course you
need, of course you need to check it. Since if there was
a hole, it would make the animal a טרפה *treifa*, right, it
would tear the animal's organs or the throat or whatever before doing
the שחיטה *shechitah*, so it would make the animal a טרפה *treifa*.
So of course you need to check it. So the גמרא *Gemara*
says, no, no, no. Obviously you need to check it for that
reason. לחכם קאמרינן *L'Chacham Ka'amrinan*. The question is, how do you know
you need a sage to check it? And that's what we learned
from the verse. That's... calm down... that's what we learned from the
verse because in the case in שמואל *Shmuel*, you did have, you
did have שמואל *Shmuel* checking it. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, והאמר
רבי יוחנן לא אמרו להראות סכין לחכם אלא מפני כבודו של חכם
*Veha'amar Rebbe Yochanan Lo Amru L'Harot Sakin L'Chacham Ela Mipnei Kvodo Shel
Chacham*? But didn't we say before that the idea of a sage
checking it was only a way of showing honor to the sage?
It was not a strict requirement. Alright, you're right. מדרבנן *Miderabbanan*, it
is only rabbinic. וקרא אסמכתא בעלמא *U'kra Asmachta B'alma*. The verse is
only some type of a support, it's not real, it's a way
that we read it into the verse and see the idea echoed
or whatever, presaged by the verse, but nevertheless it is not really
a strict requirement. Okay, but now we're introducing the idea of checking
the knife. So it says like this: במערבא *B'Ma'arava*, in the West,
in Israel, בדקי לה בשמשא *Badki Lei B'Shimsha*, they checked it using
the sun, meaning they looked at the sun, maybe it was like,
you know, checking your lettuce for bugs, somehow that was able to
show up more the nicks. רש״י *Rashi* maybe says also you looked
at the shadow. The shadow is larger and also it's more of
a contrast, so it's easier to see if it's not exactly straight
by looking at the shadow. בנהרדעא *B'Neharde'a*, in Neharde'a, בדקי לה במיא
*Badki Lei B'Maya*, they used water. What does this mean? רש״י *Rashi*
gives two explanations. One is you rub the edge of the knife,
you know, you hold the knife sort of parallel to the water
surface, you rub it against the water surface and you see whether
the water that flows, you know, directly under, whether it changes its,
you know, current in any place. If there's a nick in the
knife, then somehow, you know, that'll obviously be affected by the way
the water is running under the knife. The other possibility רש״י *Rashi*
says is you take a drop of water and you hold the
knife sort of, you know, vertical, or at a slight angle. You
take a drop of water, and if the drop runs straight down
the knife, there's no nick. But if there's a nick, as the
drop is running down it'll get caught and it'll hesitate for a
moment before continuing down. Go ahead and test those. Okay. רב ששת
*Rav Sheshet* בדקי לה בריש לישנא *Badki Lei B'Reish Lishna*. רב ששת
*Rav Sheshet* tested it with the tip of his tongue. The tip
of his tongue. Oh, that's interesting. I didn't think about that. He
was blind, but he could use his finger. The tip of your
tongue, you gotta be very delicate so as not to cut, and
you could obviously it's super sensitive, the tip of your tongue, so
you'll catch the slight nick. There used to be... there are some
experts that can still touch test שחיטה *shechitah* knives with their tongue.
Tongue, if you're not careful, I suppose. Okay. רב אחא בר יעקב
*Rav Acha Bar Yaakov* בדקי לה בחוט השערה *Badki Lei B'Chut Ha'sa'arah*.
רב אחא בר יעקב *Rav Acha Bar Yaakov* used a hair, obviously
he held it perpendicular to the edge, ran it against the edge,
it would get caught if it would hit
a nick. בסורא אמרי *B'Sura Amri*, in Sura they say, בשרא אכלה
בשרא לבדקה levadka, *Bisra Achla Bisra Livdika*. They say, look, well, this
knife is made for eating, cutting meat, so you should touch test
it with meat, with flesh. Meaning, you don't have to be so
hypersensitive, you know, to test it with a microscope, to test it
with your, you know, tongue. It might be that your tongue can
detect a nick, but it's not enough of a nick that it's
going to be a problem in the act of שחיטה *shechitah*. So
therefore, שחיטה *shechitah* is about cutting meat, so you test it with
meat. What does meat mean? Your fingertip. So use your fingertip, we're
going to see in a minute to test it, but it doesn't
have to be more sensitive than that because that's how it's being
used. Okay. אמר רב פפא *Amar Rav Pappa*, צריכה בדיקה אבישרא ואטופרא
*Tzricha Bdika A'bisra V'atufra*. You have to test it with the flesh,
meaning your fingertip,
and also on your fingernail. Okay, now why... and some say also
ואתלתא רוחתא *V'atlata Ruchta*, on three sides, meaning the edge, and also,
you know, the edge sort of if you, you know, V's up,
right? The edge is, you know, if the knife is coming to
an edge at the bottom, it sort of gets sharpened down like
that. So also at those edges, the up of the V, the
sides, not just the very tip itself. So now we're going to
look at this.
אמר ליה Amar leh, רבינא לרב אשי *Amar Lei Ravina L'Rav Ashi*,
אמר לן רב סמא בריה דרב משארשיא משמך *Amar Lan Rav Sama
Brei D'Rav Mesharshiya Mishmach*, דאמרת ליה משמיה דרבא *D'amart Lei Mishmei D'Rava*,
צריכה בדיקה אבישרא *Tzricha Bdika A'bisra*, that you have to do a
test on flesh, on the fingertip,
ואטופרא *V'atufra*, on the
fingernail, ואתלתא רוחתא *V'atlata Ruchta*, and on the three edges.
Three edges. What?
אמר ליה, so he said back to him, אבשרא ואטופרא אמרי, A-bishra
va-tupra amri, I did say it's true about the fingertip and the
nail, but ואתלתא רויחתא לא אמרי, va-tlata rivchata lo amri, I did
not say all three sides. איכא דאמרי, Ika de-amri, some say אבשרא
ואטופרא ואתלתא רויחתא אמרי, A-bishra va-tupra va-tlata rivchata amri, yes I did
say the tip, the fingertip, the nail and the three sides, but
משמיה דרבא לא אמרי, mishmeih de-Rava lo amri, I didn't say it
in the name of רבא. Rava. Okay, that was a less interesting
correction. So what's the conclusion of this? אמרי רבינא ורב אחא בריה
דרבא, Amri Ravina ve-Rav Acha breih de-Rava, I didn't say, רבינא ורב
אחא בריה דרבא הוו יתבי קמיה דרב אשי, Ravina ve-Rav Acha breih
de-Rava havu yasvei kameih de-Rav Ashi, so they were sitting in front
of רב אשי. Rav Ashi. אייתו סכינא קמיה דרב אשי Aito sakkina
kameih de-Rav Ashi לבדקה, so somebody was following the rule and he
brought his knife in front of רב אשי Rav Ashi to check
it. אמר ליה לרב אחא בריה דרבא בדקה. Amar leh le-Rav Acha
breih de-Rava badka. So רב אשי Rav Ashi gave it to one
of his students, he said to רב אחא בריה דרבא, Rav Acha
breih de-Rava, here you check it. בדקה אטופרא ואבשרא, Badka atupra ve-abishra,
he checked it with his fingernail and with the flesh of his
finger,
ואתלתא רויחתא. ve-atlata revachta. אמר ליה, so רב אשי Rav Ashi said
to him, יישר ישר כוח, Yiasher yashar koach, good, you did the
right thing, וכן אמר רב כהנא, ve-chein amar Rav Kahana, and this
is what רב כהנא Rav Kahana says that you should do it
exactly that way. רב יימר אמר, Rav Yemar amar, רב יימר Rav
Yemar disagreed, he says אטופרא ואבשרא צריכא, atupra ve-abishra tzericha, on the
fingernail and on the flesh you need it, אתלתא רויחתא לא צריכא,
atlata rivchata lo tzericha, you don't need it on all three sides,
you only need it at the very edge, not at the sides.
Why? מי לא אמר רב זירא אמר שמואל, Mi lo amar Rav
Zeira amar Shmuel, cause רב זירא Rav Zeira says in the name
of שמואל, remember this from about a week or two ago? ליבן
סכין ושחט בה שחיטתו כשרה, Liben sakkina ve-shachat bah shechitatah kesherah, if
you have a red hot knife, a white hot knife, and you
שחט, it's okay, we assume that it's the sharpness that cuts and
not burning. שחידודה, She-chidudah, the sharpness, קודם לליבונה kodem le-libunah precedes the
burning, וקשיא לן, ve-kashya lan, we asked a question, היכא צדדין, heika
tzdadin, it's very nice, but as you keep on going into the
throat, the edges of the knife that are white hot will burn
the throat, why are we not and cause it to become a
טרפה, why are we not concerned about that? ואמרינן, Ve-amrinan, and we
answered, בית השחיטה מירוח רווח, beit ha-shechitah mirvach ravach, because as you
cut the throat, the incision opens up, so the edges of your
knife are not touching any part of the meat cause as you're
cutting it's opening up, and therefore we don't have to be concerned
about the fact that it's red hot or white hot. So if
that's true, הכא נמי, hacha nami, here too, בית השחיטה מירוח רווח,
beit ha-shechitah mirvach ravach, we should say the same thing that it
opens up and I don't care about the edges of the knife,
I only care about the tip of the knife. And although this
makes a lot of sense, רש"י Rashi says although we said all
that, in the end we do check the edges of the knife
as well, not just, not the tip is the wrong phrase, tip
sounds like it's the point, meaning the edge of the knife and
the sides, I should be saying the sides, the edge of the
knife as well as not the whole sides but where the sides
angle into, you know, the edge, as you're sharpening it where the
sides angle into the edge. One last comment, why do you check
the finger nail? What about the point about checking if it's cutting
meat? So תוספות Tosafot says you're checking the finger nail cause you're
cutting also the trachea and the trachea's hard, so therefore you're checking
the finger nail to see as to how if it's gonna do
any tearing when it hits the trachea, so you use your finger
nail as a test for that. Okay.